Guide to the International Monitor Institute. Rwanda Videotapes and Audiotapes, 1992-1999 RL.00607
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Rwanda Audiotapes Series (Audiocassette), 1993-1994, 8 boxes
  - CE.90/95, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW183)
    Commentaires sur le conseil du gouvernement antérieurement programmé et qui a été annulé sur le Premier Ministre Madame Uqiringiyimana Agathe et sur la prestation de serment prévue pour ce jour à 15 h.
    Commentaire sur le procès intenté contre Twagiramungu par certains députés du MDR à qui il aurait interdit de participer dans les institutions de transition à base élargie et sur ces institutions en général.
    Lecture d'une lettre d'un membre du parti PDC à propos de ces mêmes institutions. Commentaires.
    Reportage de Georges Ruggiu en français au retour des lieux où devait avoir lieu la prestation de serment.
    Face BL
    Suite du reportage de Ruggiu. Interview de Barayagwiza sur ce blocage.
    Commentaires de Valérie sur les personnes qui avaient été invitées à ces cérémonies.
    Reportage de Nkomati Emmanuel sur cette cérémonie en kinyarwanda.
    Commentaires de Valérie et Nkomati
  - CE.92/95, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW184)
    Noel's comments on the situation in HYPOTHEQUE Secondary School.
    Noel's criticism on rich businessmen who didn't contribute to reward Rayons Sport Club.
    Noel's comments on RPF's absence to come to the ceremony of taking the oath
    Noel accuses Kagame of being responsible for the lives of youth who are dying on the battlefield
    Ruggiu's report of the participants to the failed ceremony of the establishment of transtiional institutions.
    Ruggiu's comments on Arusah agreement.
    Side B: Ruggiu's comments on Rwanda's economical and political problems
    Ruggiu's comments on RPF's plans: preparation of a war
    Communiqué on the establishment of the transitions institutions with or without the participation of RPF.
    Interview of Jean Bosco Barayagwiza on the political blockade.
    Broadcast on AIDS, on the thalidomide medicine.
    Nkomati's comments on the failed ceremony of the day before: formation of the Extended Transitional Government and taking the oath for the Members of Parliament.
  - C.51/K 95, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW185)
    Air Date: 1994 Mar. 29-30
    Interview du Procureur général de la Cour de Cassation Mbarushimana Bonaventure par Gagigi Gaspard à propose du refus de Nzamurambaho de répondre à la convocation lui adressée dans le cadre des enquêtes sur l'assassinat de Félicien Gatabazi.
    Commentaires sur ce sujet et sur Nzamurambaho en général.
    Interview de Nkurunziza Ananie par Gahigi Gaspard sur les problèmes de la famine dans la préfecture de Gikongoro, sur les problèmes politiques y causés par le même Nzamurambaho, sur l'assassinat de Gatabazi...
    Hymne national
    Journaliste: Hitimana Noèl
    Commentaire sur la convocation que lui a adressée la parquet
    Commentaires sur la manifestation des étudiantes de la Faculté de Droit, à propos d'un chauffeur de l'ONATRACOM, Munyagasiza Fidèle.
    Commentaire sur les explications que vient de lui donner chauffeur.
    Commentaire sur la déclaration No. 20 de la communauté des étudiants Rwandais en Belguique.
    Commentaire à propose des directeurs de écoles qui ne permettent pas à leurs élèves d'écouter la RTLM.
    Commentaires divers.
    Commentaire sur le fait que la CDR s'apprête à attaquer le Premier Ministre Uwiringiyimana Agathe parce qu'elle l'aurait accusée injustement de génocide et sur la lettre que le MDR power a adressée au même Premier Ministre le 1994 Mar. 28 disant que c'est Kamali qui doit être député du MDR pour la préfecture de Gisenyi dans l'Assemblée Nationale de transition.
    Commentaires sur le problèmes des Tutsi de la commune Kanzenze.
  - C.52/K 95, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW186)
    Air Date: 1994 Mar. 30
  - C.53/K 95, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW187)
    An unidentified journalist states that the CDR should be allowed to participate in the transitional government. Ruggiu then reports that the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF)'s Radio Muhabura is waging a war of disinformation and blaming the CDR and MDR for crimes committed in the demilitarized zone. Rucogoza follows with a report about the student demonstrations at the Faculty of Law in Kigali. He interviews two students, Viateur Kamali and Félix Aimable Mujyambere who deny the notion that the demonstrations have a political background. Rucogoza then interviews Dr. Jean Gakwaya, Dean of the Faculty of Law at Kigali, who is of the opinion that the crisis at the university is linked to the current political and socio-economic troubles prevalent throughout Rwanda. Ruggiu then implies that the Belgians are "blackmailing" Rwanda. A conversation between Ruggiu and Gahigi follows. They discuss the RPF's "infiltration" plots, the fact that the "enemy is known" and the RPF's unwillingness to share power. Their conversation is interspersed with reports that a certain Jean Ndamiye's house is under attack in Kiyovu. Mr. Katumba's death is mentioned as well as an incident that took place in Karago. At one point Ruggiu muses about why "some MRND and CDR militants are regularly attacked." Towards the end of the cassette Kantano comes on to report that Mr. Niyongira in Muyira apparently plotted against an MP Muhutu. Kantano hopes that the people of Muyira are listening. Rucogoza and Mbilizi end the tape with the following comments: 1) Should General Dallaire continue as commander of the UNAMIR? 2) the RPF has recruited 13 students out of Nyanza. 3) The RPF has no right to prevent the CDR from participation in the transitional parliament.
  - C.54/K 95, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW188A)
    Air Date: 1994 Mar. 31
    Kantano begins the tape retracting an earlier statement alleging that Christophe Bazivamo is an "Inyenzi." He then targets Justin Niyongira and a number of "collaborators" including Balthazar Bazatoba, Silas Ruzinda and Conseiller Theobald Rutaganzwa. Niyongira in particular is accused of allowing members of the PSD and of his ethnic group of committing murder without having to face punishment. Mbilizi then interviews Stanislas Simbizi of the CDR who it is said has just "narrowly escaped" an attempt on his life. Simbizi accuses the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) of committing atrocities and of being unwilling to participate in a peaceful democratic process. Rucogoza then provides an eerie description of the "gloomy" atmosphere pervading Kigali city. Mbilizi follows with a list of students from Nyanza said to have formed the "Inziraguteba Brigade" with the intent of joining the RPF. Mbilizi then addresses the conflict between the CDR and the RPF about the CDR's participation in the Transitional National Assembly.
  - C.54/K 95, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW188B)
    Double-check air date. The tape appears to begin with a broadcast from the night of March 31, 1994. However, the tape apparently ends the following morning April 1, 1994.
    Mbilizi begins the tape reading from a letter addressed to Prime Minister Uwilingiyimana from eleven Ministers in her Cabinet. The letter is a criticism of Uwilingiyimana and implies that she has inappropriate contact with the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF). Mbilizi then launches into a monologue about the difficulty of implementing the Arusha Accords and particularly the problems the RPF are creating by opposing the CDR's entry into the Transitional National Assembly. He also accuses the RPF of committing atrocities. Ruggiu follows with an interview of Gahigi. Among other things they touch on the true face of the RPF and its desire for power. Gahigi also predicts a "total war" should fighting break out again.
  - C.55/K 95, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW189A)
    Air Date: 1994 Apr. 01
    The translator appears to have summarized parts of the tape (see record #14, end of transcript).
    Bemeriki begins the tape with a communiqué from the Laurien Karumuhinzi, Secretary General of the Democratic Party. Karumuhinzi extends his party's support to the CDR in their fight to gain entry into the Transitional National Assembly. Hitimana follows with a long monologue in which he targets two men, Dr. Ngirabanyiginya and Dr. Iyamuremye, for responsibility in the death of Katumba, a member of the CDR. Hitimana also targets two employees of the Department of Taxes, Albert Niyotwilingiye and Immaculee Bamurange, for allegedly offering a reward to Katumba's killer. Hitimana implies that the Inkotanyi are the source of the murder. He ends the tape with an analysis of the major parties during which several party leaders are targeted as particularly inefficient or as having ties to the Inkotanyi. The MRND's woes are blamed on the war and the CDR is lauded as the only party with the population's interests at heart.
  - C.55/K 95, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW189B)
    Again, as in Archive #189A, there are two sections (records 1 and 8) where the translator did not translate the text.
    Nkomati begins the tape attacking the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) for their statements broadcasted on Radio Rwanda in which they criticize the government, intellectuals and journalists. He then proceeds to summarize the letter written by the Democratic Party in support of the CDR's participation in the Transitional National Assembly. Gahigi follows with an on-site report of a grenade attack directed against Thomas Kabonabake, editor of the newspaper "Echo des Milles Collines." Kabonabake explains that it is the second such attack and the he suspects his "Tutsi neighbors" and their accomplices. He also suggests that the Inkotanyi have informants among the Rwandan population who report back to the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) leaders staying at the CND.
  - C.56/K 95, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW190)
  - C.57/K 95, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW191)
  - C.58/K 95, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW192)
    Air Date: 1994 Apr. 3
  - C.59/K 95, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW193)
  - C.60/K 95, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW194)
  - C.62/K 95, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW195)
    Air Date: 1994 ,au 28-29
  - RSF K7 No. 1, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW196)
    Producer: Reporters San Frontières
  - RSF K7 No. 2, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW197)
  - RSF K7 No. 3, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW198)
  - RSF K7 No. 4, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW199)
  - RSF K7 No. 5, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW200)
  - RSF K7 No. 6, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW201)
  - RSF K7 No. 7, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW202)
  - RSF K 7 No. 8, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW203)
  - RSF K7 No. 9, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW204)
  - RSF K7 No. 10, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW205)
  - RSF K7 No. 11, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW206)
  - RSF K7 No. 12, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW207)
  - RSF K7 No. 13, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW208)
  - RSF K7 No. 14, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW209)
  - RSF K7 No. 15, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW210)
    Air Date: [not available
  - RSF K7 No. 16, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW211)
  - RSF K7 No. 17, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW212)
  - RSF K7 No. 18, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW213)
  - RSF K7 No. 19, Sony HF 60 (Box 124, Audio-cassette RW214)
  - RSF K7 No. 20, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW215)
  - RSF K7 No. 21, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW216)
  - RSF K7 No. 22, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW217)
  - RSF K7 No. 23, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW218)
  - RSF K7 No. 24, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW219)
  - RSF K7 No. 25, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW220)
  - RSF K7 No. 26, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW221)
  - RSF K7 No. 27, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW222)
  - RSF K7 No. 28, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW223)
  - RSF K7 No. 29, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW224)
  - RSF K7 No. 30, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW225)
  - RSF K7 No. 31, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW226)
  - RSF K7 No. 32, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW227)
  - RSF K7 No. 33, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW28)
  - RSF K7 No. 34, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW229)
  - RSF K7 No. 35, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW230)
  - RSF K7 No. 36, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW231)
  - RSF K7 No. 37, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW232)
  - RSF K7 No. 38, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW233)
  - RSF K7 No. 39, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW234)
  - RSF K7 No. 40, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW235)
  - RSF K7 No. 41, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW236)
  - RSF K7 No. 42, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW237)
  - RSF K7 No. 43, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW238)
  - RSF K7 No. 44, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW239)
  - RSF K7 No. 45, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW240)
  - RSF K7 No. 46, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW241)
  - RSF K7 No. 47, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW242)
  - RSF K7 No. 48, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW243)
  - RSF K7 No. 49, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW244)
  - RSF K7 No. 50, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW245)
  - RSF K7 No. 51, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW246)
  - RSF K7 No. 52, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW247)
  - RSF K7 No. 53, Sony HF 60 (Box 125, Audio-cassette RW248)
  - RSF K7 No. 54, Sony HF 60 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW249)
  - RSF K7 No. 55, Sony HF 60 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW250)
  - RSF K7 No. 56, Sony HF 60 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW251)
  - RSF K7 No. 57, Sony HF 60 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW252)
  - RSF K7 No. 58, Sony HF 60 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW253)
  - RSF K7 No. 59, Sony HF 60 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW254)
  - RSF K7 No. 60, Sony HF 60 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW255)
  - RSF K7 No. 61, Sony HF 60 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW256)
  - RSF K7 No. 62, Sony HF 60 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW257)
  - RSF K7 No. 63, Sony HF 60 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW258)
  - RSF K7 No. 64, Sony HF 60 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW259)
  - A7: V. Meersch, Sony HiFi 90 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW260)
  - A6: V. Meersch, Sony HiFi 90 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW261)
  - B5: V. Meersch, Sony HiFi 90 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW262)
  - A4: V. Meersch, Sony HiFi 90 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW263)
  - A3: V. Meersch, Sony HiFi 90 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW264)
  - A2: V. Meersch, Sony HiFi 90 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW265)
  - A1: V. Meersch, Sony HiFi 90 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW266)
  - RTLM 20, Sony HiFi 90 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW267)
    Air Date: 1994 June 3 and 11
    Animation de Bemeriki Valérie et de Nkurunziza Ananie.
    Break of Arusha Agreement by RPF.
    Interview of Kajuga J. Pierre addressing Byumba displaced population.
    About Catholic bishops.
    Ananie ethnic comments on Nayakakanda High Seminary.
    Face B: Idem (almost inaudible).
  - RTLM, Sony HiFi 90 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW268)
    No description available
  - CD copies of audiotape recordings, 1993-1994, TDK CD-R74 (40 discs (Box 127)
- Rwanda Audiotapes Series (Electronic Records), 1993-1994, 1 box; 62 folders, 654 files, 7.04 GB
  Series contains digital files related to the RTLM audio cassettes. The Documents folder (389 files; 426 MB) includes transcripts, tape logs, and court documents related to the translation and transcription of the audio cassettes. Files are in .tiff format. The Audio folder (266 files; 11 folders; 6,791 MB) contains digital surrogates of many of the audio cassettes. Files are in MP3 format. The MP3 files are listed by their Exhibit number. A cross index between RTLM number and the Exhibit number is available in Box 719.
  Electronic records have been migrated to a library server. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
  - Digitized documents, 388 files; approximately 500 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL00607-SET-0001)
    Scope and Contents
    Digitized documents in TIFF format.
  - Audio files, 266 files; approximately 6.5 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL00607-SET-0001)
    Audio files in MP3 format.
  - List of RTLM tapes (Box 719)